Kristof wibicki he pulled 510 kg but
there are some big caveats to this 510
kg AKA
1,125 lb pull so you would think you
would want as many opportunities to see
which athletes you're going to send as
possible and China's like nah we're
going to win it all anyway so what does
it matter and look Duda he didn't come
out of nowhere last year but he's
surprised folks who's to say someone
couldn't do that this
year welcome to strength weekly the
weekly internet YouTube digital show
whatever you want to call it that brings
you everything you need know from around
the barbell game I am one of your hosts
David Thomas to I am joined by the
incomparable the Irreplaceable Beyonce
voice Phil blechman and we are bringing
you some big lifts big news and previews
from around the strength Sports World
The Run of show today on strength weekly
we are covering Kristoff whz bicki
deadlifting 510 kgs beltless and off the
blocks in training this is not a world
record this is not even a competition
lift so how do we contextualize massive
feat of strength like this Phil and I
are going to dive into that and maybe
argue gez I hope so our second segment
team China withdraws from the 2024 Asian
weightlifting championships waight team
China the most dominant weightlifting
team in the world for nearly two decades
withdrawing from a major competition
just months before the Paris Olympics
segment 3A new study reveals two
training techniques to maximize muscle
growth some new research peels back the
curtain on our biology and there are
some really important takeaways for how
to gain strength and size if you're
looking to do those two things and
segment four the biggest bodybuilders in
the world will throw down at the 2024
Arnold Classic men's open division the
first weekend in March Phil Blackman
what are you most excited about today
when it comes to this I don't mean what
you had for breakfast or what you're
going to have for lunch I always get
excited to talk about the Arnold uh
classic but I mean the weightlifting
news is kind of big in an Olympics year
it's kind of real big kind of big kind
of big kind of big but Phil first
and foremost Kristoff whs bicki he
pulled 510 kilogram this under different
circumstances would be the heaviest
deadlift of all time the heaviest weight
that anyone has ever put on a barbell
and lifted off the ground to full
lockout but there are some big caveats
to this 510 kilogram AKA
1,125 pound is pull what do we need to
start keeping in mind when we hear about
big lifts like this because this is
impactful this is historic yeah what
does it count for it doesn't actually
count for anything other than our
entertainment and you know where the
possibilities for mankind could go we
bicki pulled 510 kgrs off of blocks now
they're not like the blocks that are at
his hips you know they they were Low
Blocks but they it was not a pull from
the floor and he pulled it in Sumo which
is not conventional so we were going to
get into that a little bit by comparing
what a conventional LIF is to Sumo and I
know that who doesn't love talking about
that who it's a very it's a very cious
and cordial debate and then no one has
no one has ever physically threatened
anyone in the comment section of social
media over the Sumo versus conventional
debate that much I know of this is
sarcasm this is sarcasm people go off on
this I have never been personally
threatened over my preference of
deadlifting so uh once you get up into
this space this nebulous space of the
heaviest ever there are so many
different things that can affect what
that actually means because there's no
necessarily standardized things so it's
really just here's what humans are
theoretically capable of and we bicki is
at the Forefront of that now even though
he did do this deadlift off of blocks
and he used lifting straps because who
has a grip to hold that much weight one
thing that he didn't do which he's been
now notorious for at least in our
coverage of him dude does not use a belt
like the posterior chain on this guy is
insane like he's just like yeah I'll
lift this thing I don't need any I I can
brace myself I don't need any equipment
maybe my grip isn't necessarily that of
the hulks but I I don't need help from a
belt guys brace yourself Thanos style to
continue the uh Marvel C itic Universe
reference I'll do it myself I don't need
no belt here's the thing about
powerlifting you can deadlift
conventional or you can deadlift Sumo
you cannot use straps and depending on
the competition you may be able to use
the lifting suit or not right you can
certainly use a Bell he just decided not
to compare that to Strongman Competition
which is the format that something like
the world deadlift championships is
contested in you cannot lift Sumo you
can only lift conventional but you can
lift equipped and you can use straps in
fact you can use those figure eight
straps that like lock your wrists onto
the bar right so there are two basic
types of deadlift competition that we
cover at barbend powerlifting Sumo okay
straps no okay strongman straps okay
Sumo no okay a lot of these that are
sumo with streps don't count in either
of those Realms of competition I just
want to be very clear here so is this a
world record from the like standpoint of
it's contested right and there are
judges no absolutely not especially
because this one was off the blocks
let's be honest this is really just an
example we're using to illustrate that
like these don't necessarily count for
anything but there's this weird in
between this middle of the VIN diagram
when you use straps and you suuma we see
the heaviest weights of all time being
pulled but they're not going into the
record books Phil I think you put it
very well they're just showing maybe
what the human body is capable of right
but they're not contested so they're not
World Records it might be the heaviest
weight of all time but it's not a world
record but that's to contextualize it
these are impressive Feats but they're
Feats they're not competitive lifts
maybe
someday someone will hold a competition
where the barbell and calibrated plates
are standardized and you can lift with
straps in Sumo it is not today and it is
not us when we cover these uh events and
we cover actual world record deadlifts I
like having these sort of lifts in the
back pocket knowing for like what the
top end of the range is so when you see
a big guy like Jamal Browner or whoever
pull an insanely heavy deadlift of you
know like you know 490 kilos or whatever
you're like okay I know that the
heaviest we have ever seen on camera
ever in any capacity is 510 and if this
dude is not using blocks and is not
using straps and is you know pulling raw
at you know 20 kilos under that that is
unbelievably close to what the heaviest
ever seen is with equipment so I like it
as a gauge as a reference point and as
you said it helps contextualize how
heavy the actual competition the
sanction competition LS actually are we
cover this stuff it's interesting it's
good context because we're trying to
bring you everything you need to know
from around the barbell game but we're
not calling it a record we're not we're
not taking those editorial Liberties
let's talk about something we also
didn't take editorial liberties with and
moved to the world of weightlifting Phil
because team China the most dominant
force in international weightlifting for
nearly two decades has withdrawn from
the 2024 Asian weightlifting
championships and I want to point out uh
barbend basically broke this story not
to not to brush our shoulders off not to
T our own horn too much uh but Brian
Oliver who is a noted and very
accomplished weightlifting uh journalist
who recently started writing for barbend
verified this news uh with some
documents that were not made public just
yet but team China has withdrawn which
very much changes the landscape of the
Asian weightlifting championships this
year Phil why else is this a bit of a
head scratcher SL something we should
pay attention to this is a head
scratcher on our end because it's an
Olympic Games year and the quota of
athletes that are going to be able to
compete at in Paris for weightlifting is
limited so you would think you would
want as many opportunities to see which
athletes you're going to send as
possible and China's like nah we're
going to win it all anyway so what does
it matter yeah it it's interesting
because like the question for China is
like their roster so deep who are they
gonna send right because they can only
send one lifter per weight category
right especially with the cut in Quota
for athletes for the number of athletes
who can compete at weightlifting in
Paris it's going to be a very small
number relative to previous Olympics
Cycles so we know at China's going to
send a full team it's just we got some
question marked in certain weight
categories who are they going to send
these International competitions are
often a way to figure out who's showing
up stronger and it's just one fewer
opportunity for them to do that now the
Asian weight championships is scheduled
for early February in tesan usbekistan
China will not be there this definitely
opens up some possibilities for other
folks to take home some medals in those
way categories it really changes the
field there is one final Olympic
qualifying event China has not withdrawn
from it's the IW World Cup a little
later this year I do want to read a
quote from a representative of the
Chinese National weightlifting team to
ensure the systematic winter training of
our athletes and adjust their Rhythm for
competition after careful consideration
we have decided to participate in the
Thailand World Cup scheduled at the end
of March which is also a compulsory
qualification event and that that they
were giving that quote in response to
withdrawing from the Asian weightlifting
Championship so there you go we'll see
him in Thailand we won't see him in
usbekistan Phil speaking of very strong
people it wasn't until recent decades
that we really knew how the human body
gained strength and muscle size like we
knew what hypertrophy was but we didn't
know a lot about the biology sort of
like we don't know a lot about why
humans sleep or the mechanics behind it
two studies came out and studies come
out a lot we report on these on barbin
but these had really interesting
potentially direct implications for
folks who are training in the gym and
how to maximize their training Phil do
you want to give us the rundown of what
these two techniques are uh that we now
know a lot more about have more
peer-reviewed research behind yeah
there's been a a recent like flood of
research that has been embracing the the
notion that training your muscles in
their lengthened positions is more
favorable for hypertrophy if you were to
do a bicep curl where you're staying in
your shortened uh range of motion
towards your Peak contraction that's
when your muscle is at its shortest
right it's the peak most Peak contracted
position of the muscle now in its fully
lengthened position that is the portion
where a lot of research has showed that
like the activation when it's in its
lengthen position it's put put under
stimulus in its lengthened position is
where it's actually going to grow the
most after the fact the other uh big
takeaway that they have found in this
study at least is how long each rep
should take during a set now they uh
agreed that going to muscular failure
which is when your form starts to break
down is still good for hypertrophy that
wasn't questioned they they reinforced
that the takeaway that they did have was
how long each rep should take on route
to muscular failure and that they said
should be around the 2 to 8 second range
now that a long range for if you do uh
fast reps you'd be surprised how long 2
seconds actually is when you perform a
rep like if you're not thinking about it
you move the Reps way faster than that
so two to eight seconds is a really
really wide range the caveat that really
stuck out to me was explosive
concentrics are still valuable like that
that is still shown to remain effective
for hypertrophy extending your
eccentrics so the negative portion of
your lift extending that for more time
to get within that 2 to8 second range is
where they're saying it's off off
setting gravity taking hold of the lift
so if you allow the weight to move down
too fast gravity is probably offsetting
a bunch of the the stimulus that would
be placed on your muscle during that
Ecentric and they're saying by resisting
that by allowing the muscle to actually
move through its Ecentric to lower the
weight take more time and that's where
you're going to see more gains and
that's where they found L working in the
lengthen position which is what you're
doing when you move into the Ecentric
phase of the lift is where there's gains
to be had that if you're not doing your
leaving on the table
Phil can you give us examples on these
two techniques like how One might
Implement those into one's training for
example yeah so let's say for let's just
make it easy and we'll do a bicep curl
okay okay bicep curl let's talk about
the first the first technique which is
training in the length and position of
the muscle yes so if you're doing a
bicep curl if you are at the bottom of
the movement you want to put some amount
of stimulus in the lengthen position
this is where something like working
with cables and having uh a moment arm a
little bit of physics but having a
moment arm where there is some amount of
tension placed on the muscle in the
lengthen position to maintain that
position so if you use a barbell and you
just have it hanging down gravity is
doing all the work there right that's a
position of rest there isn't any
stimulus placed on the biceps if you use
a cable and you're facing away from the
cable machine and you have a a little
bit of pull while you're in the fully
lengthen position your arm is straight
there's still a little bit of that
tension that tension is being held in
the biceps to hold that position before
you actually move into your contraction
you want to have stimulus and you want
to have force exerted on you want the
muscle to be exerting Force at the
length of position so for example the
bottom of a bicep curl as opposed to the
top of a bicep curl because the muscle
is in a lengthened position at the
bottom of the curl it's in a shortened
position at the top so let's say you
actually reach the end of your set you
go to muscular failure you're going to
do a drop set but you're going to do
partials because your form has faltered
doing those partials in the length in
position where your muscle is longer so
the bottom half of the range that is
going to likely lead to more hypertrophy
gains based on this study than working
in the shorten Position will now there's
gains for both you should like still do
both there isn't anything to say that
working in the shorten position is
obsoleted or anything but this study is
showing that there is more effect to be
had for hypertrophy gains working in the
lengthen position by doing that you know
the biggest takeaway from this full
range of motion on the pull-ups folks
full range of motion go all the way down
because that's going to create more
tension on the muscle for both the bicep
which is in the length in position and
the lats which are also in the lengthen
position at the bottom there okay Phil
uh let's give an example of the second
takeaway from this study yes so the
second takeaway is the essentially rep
Tempo how much time each rep should take
and they gave a very wide range of two
to eight seconds as previously mentioned
and what that means from a practical
standpoint is if you explode through the
concentric and you have a a strong bicep
curl that's okay but when you lower the
the weight you should take more time to
lower the weight and more time is really
just like okay if it takes a quick
moment to actually lift the weight
lowering for two seconds is more
difficult than it seems I promise you
it's it's a lot harder than it seems
especially when you get to the back end
of a set so just slow your eccentrics
down and that will likely lead to more
hypertrophy gains over the course of a
longer a long program and just to
reiterate folks if you want to learn
more we have this covered at barbend uh
but the narrative study was titled
optimizing resistance training technique
to maximize hypertrophy a narrative
review it was published in the Journal
of functional morphology and
kinesthesiology uh some names that you
might have heard of if you are in the
fitness influencer and research space
Jeff nippard uh who is a longtime
content creator in the space Brad
shenfeld and uh Milo wolf all involved
in uh in this narrative study so pretty
interesting stuff well we have a preview
of probably the second biggest
bodybuilding competition in the calendar
year yeah second biggest and that is the
Arnold Classic men's open division we
have 12 competitors slated to take to
the stage in Columbus Ohio in early
March Phil who are some of the big names
who will be competing so the returning
Champion Sams s DOTA is going to be in
uh Columbus he will be there to defend
his title as well as a former Mr Olympia
Champion hadti chupen is going to be in
Columbus Ohio as well he was the runner
up in 2023 after dropping the title to
drik Lansford and he's got to get some
momentum back yes the Arnold Classic is
pretty much widely accepted as the
second big biggest bodybuilding show of
the Year behind the Olympia pretty
pretty clear there's no debate about
that really there are 12 competitors in
this show it feels and I would be
surprised if it's not just a two- horse
race it's going to be chupen versus daa
for the title they were in the top three
at the Mr Olympia a couple months back
and they will be fighting for this again
now if daa defends and beats chupan here
that would Bode very well for what daa's
trajectory looks like in the Olympia
later in 2024 because shupin beat daa at
the 2023 Olympia shuin got second D got
third Derrik lford obviously got first
so if they go into the Olympia where
chupen is slipping down ranks over two
major competitions that VES extremely
well for Duda now if chupan beats Duda
then we will likely see the rematch of
chupan versus Lunsford for the title in
2024 unless Duda makes some significant
changes and look Duda he didn't come out
of nowhere last year but he surprised
folks who's to say someone couldn't do
that this year as well you know what I
mean it's always fun to see some
surprises and I think duda's emergence
as one of the top competitors in the
men's open division was up pleasant
surprise for fans last year it really
shook things up and has continued to
have Ripple effects through the
bodybuilding space in the men's open
division so fun fun fun stuff this is a
fun competition our first chance in the
year to see the top guys conditioned and
on stage in Columbus for uh a little bit
of a recap last year it was pretty
expected that Nick Walker was the front
winner to win the Arnold Classic it just
seemed as though Walker had all of this
momentum behind him up leading up to
that competition and the upset over
Walker is what really put Duda even more
so on the map in addition to like of
course it is a huge deal when you win
the arold classic but one thing that was
notable on in the leadup to that
competition is even though Nick Walker
had all of the momentum and the clout
and the expectation daa had this like
clear respect from like all of the top
legendary bodybuilders from former eras
like Coleman and think of a major
bodybuilder like that is retired now
they were all like yeah dudo would have
been very good in our era like they like
had the they they they clearly respected
the flow of his physique and then that
happened to just resonate with the
judges as well those were the Beats
going into the 2023 Arnold going into
the 2024 Arnold it almost seems as
though daa is the favorite to defend
even though he's going against chupan so
chupan has to like somehow overcome that
like narrative that seems to be in place
because dauda has only gone on an upward
trajectory over the last year where
chupan slipped a rank now he slipped
from first in the world to second in the
world at the Olympia he still one of the
top two in the world but the momentum
feels like it's in duda's favor so what
chupan is going to do on stage to
overcome that in a subjective sport that
I think is also a very exciting aspect
to the Show excellent well Phil that
brings us to the end of strength weekly
for this year sorry for this year for
this week cuz we'll be back next week
with even more until then make sure you
like And subscribe until next time I'm
David Tomas joined by the
irles Phil Blackman thanks for tuning in
folks